<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods proclamation to the inhabitants and people of England published by one of the Lords servants ... known by the name of John Anderson.</title>
            <author>Anderson, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25350</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31900</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12273084</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12273084</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58369</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25350)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58369)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1494:43)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods proclamation to the inhabitants and people of England published by one of the Lords servants ... known by the name of John Anderson.</title>
                  <author>Anderson, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Evangelistic sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58369:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58369:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Gods Proclamation TO THE INHABITANTS AND PEOPLE OF <hi>ENGLAND.</hi> Publiſhed by one of the Lords Servants, called forth out of darkneſſe to be a Witneſs unto the Everlaſting Light of the Son of GOD.</p>
            <p>According to the Word of the Lord which came unto him on the fifth day of the ninth moneth, 1659.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Known by the name of</hi> JOHN ANDERDON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord hath ſpoken that the Rod of the wicked ſhall not alwayes be on the back of the Righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the <hi>Black ſpread Eagle</hi> at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:58369:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58369:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Epent, Repent, for the Kingdom of Heaven is at hand, and the patience and long ſuffering of God is almoſt at an end</p>
            <p>The Kingdoms of this World ſhall become the Kingdoms of the Lord, and of his Chriſt, who muſt Reign until all his enemies are ſubdued, and the greatneſs of the Dominions under the whole heavens ſhall be given into the hands of the ſaints of the moſt High God, ſuch as faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully follow the Lamb in the Regeneration, in his righteous war againſt the beaſt and falſe Prophet <hi>within</hi> and without, which have combined together to make war againſt the Lamb and his followers &amp; have given their power to the Prince of this world, the Dragon caſt out of Heaven, the Devil that old ſerpent, that hath deceived the Nations, whoſe followers ye are that rebel againſt the <hi>light,</hi> and love darkenſs rather than light becauſe your deeds are evil, having choſen to follow your own hearts luſts, and vain and wicked imaginations, which is out of the fear and councel of the Lord God of light and life.</p>
            <p>How long, how long, will ye turn the truth of God into a lye? and the glory of the incorruptible God into an image made like unto corruptible man, whoſe breath is in his noſtrils? How long will men forſake the Lord, the Fountain of living waters, and draw waters out of broken Ciſterns full of pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and defilements? How long will ye follow after vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and forſake your own mercies? How long will ye ſeek the living amongſt the dead? How long will ye follow the <hi>builders of</hi> Babel, <hi>whoſe Language is confounded with many Tongues,</hi> and ſet at nought, Chriſt Jeſus the chief corner ſtone, whoſe building is in ſpirit and truth, a City whoſe maker and bulider is God, which is at unity within it ſelf? How long will ye follow after lyes, and heap up to your ſelves teachers after your own corrupt hearts luſts, that juſtifie the Wicked and condemn the Juſt, that call good evil, and evil good, that put Light for Darkneſs, and Darkneſs for Light, and refuſe to be taught and led by the ſpirit of truth,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58369:3"/>which will lead you out of your own inventions <hi>(out of the impure)</hi> into the pure way and worſhip of God, which is in ſpirit and in truth?</p>
            <p>How long will ye cry up a Kingdom without in words, and neglect to ſeek to know <hi>Gods Kingdom within</hi> in power; That in the heart where the root of the Tree is that bringeth forth evil fruit the Axe may be laid, That by the everlaſting <hi>light</hi> of the ſon of God, ye may come to ſee what is good and what is evil in your <hi>ſelves,</hi> to a clear underſtanding of the difference between the fruit of the Tree of Knowledge of good and evil, and the Fruit of the Tree of Life, unto which an enterance is no way to be had, but under the flaming ſword of Gods wrath and anger, againſt that which hath joyned to the ſeed of the Serpent, in the tranſgreſſion of man from the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Law of God. That through the Law ye may become dead to the Law, that through the death of all that is contrary to God, ye may come to know and witneſs life in your ſelves, redemption by the blood of Jeſus which ſaveth from all ſin, that ye may be no longer falſe witneſſes, to tell of things that ye have not ſeen, but that ye may all come to know the work of God wrought in your ſelves, that ye may no longer glory and boaſt in another mans line; but that through the ſenſible operation <hi>of the word of life</hi> in your ſelves, ye may all become Preachers of righteouſneſs in your Generations, according to your meaſures of what you have ſeen, taſted and handled of Gods good word of Grace: That the <hi>new birth</hi> which is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſpirit, and ſenſibly and certainly to be known and felt in the creature, through many ſore pangs and hard tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, may be brought forth; not a thing in notion, but <hi>in truth the onely way to life,</hi> without which, none can enter into Gods Kingdom; and if ye are not witneſſes of this in your ſelves, all the experiences and records thereof by others will be lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle available to you, but to ſtand as a witneſs againſt you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verily,</hi> Eternal life is of higheſt concernment, therefore ſearch and ſeek diligently, until ye find it. And certainly, ye can have no other true hopes thereof then ye witneſs a death unto ſin in your ſelves, and a Reſurrection unto life by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58369:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>the ſpirit of Chriſt; you muſt know your ſelves Gods work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip in Chriſt Jeſus, and know the ſore travel of ſoul, until ye be formed again into the likeneſs of Gods image, in him, that ye may witneſs <hi>Chriſt in you the hope of glory;</hi> all other hopes are but the hope of the hypocrites, which ſhall periſh. As ye have all been in the degeneration from God in the actual tranſgreſſion joyned to the ſeed of the ſerpent, that drew man into the fall, ſo ye muſt all actually and really know the work of regeneration in your ſelves, by the eternal power of Gods ſpirit, working out and deſtroying the works of the Devil in the creature, by joyning him again unto the Seed of God, in whom redemption and deliverance is; In the manifeſtation of the meaſure of Gods good ſpirit given to every man to profit withal, the work is to be known and waited in.</p>
            <p>That ſo in man where Satans ſeat and dominion hath been, which hath led the creature captive into ſin and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that there alſo Gods Kingdom and Dominion in Chriſt Jeſus, the power of God may be witneſſed (truth in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts) working out and deſtroying all that's contrary to the pure nature of <hi>Gods ſeed, Chriſt;</hi> That ſo by the blood of Chriſt, the righteouſneſs of God, the creature may be clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from all filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit, and redeemed up to God again by the word of reconciliation; that ſo, that which hath led the creature captive to ſin, may now be led into cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, that ſo as ſin by mans diſobedience hath reigned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death, ſo by the reſurrection of the <hi>juſt (Chriſt in us)</hi> righteouſneſs may reign unto life everlaſting; that as ye have yeelded your members to be the weapons of unrighteouſneſs unto ſin, ſo now ye may yeeld your ſelves ſervants of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs unto holineſs; Truly ſo, not in word, but in life and power is Gods Kingdome to be known and manifeſted in you.</p>
            <p>That as ye have been under Satans power in the tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and alienation from God; ſo now, by Gods eternal ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ye may be brought to be ſubjects of Gods power in <hi>Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the ſeed of God,</hi> whoſe right it is to reign in the heart, and in the World in truth and righteouſneſs. Yea, and his Kingdom is to be ſet up on top of all deceit and deceiveableneſs
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58369:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58369:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:58369:5"/>of unrighteouſneſs, which long hath fate in the ſeat of God, and lifted it ſelf above all that is called God; the Devil ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving bewitched the Nations to believe a lye, to lead them forth from that which is pure of God <hi>within,</hi> which would ſhew men the way of life, to look abroad to powers and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and inventions without conceived in ſin and brought forth in iniquity, where the Prince of this World rules, and ſo keeps men to be bond-ſlaves to himſelf, following their luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full imaginations, and he in ſubtilty keeps poſſeſſion of the houſe within as a ſtrong man armed againſt the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the <hi>ſeed of God in the heart,</hi> where Satans Kingdom muſt be deſtroyed. And ſo long as he can keep men from turning to the <hi>work of God within,</hi> he in peace keeps his hold, and ſhews the creature with his guile and deceit, as at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that the Tree of knowledge of Good and Evil (the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions and wiſdom of man in the fall) is pleaſant and good for food. But indeed and truth in the cool of the day, when <hi>Gods</hi> voice comes to be heard, it's found to be but the increaſe of ſorrow, and bitterneſs to the ſoul, when by the everlaſting <hi>Light</hi> of the Son of God all falſe coverings and pretences are made manifeſt, and in Gods wiſdom <hi>(Chriſt in us)</hi> all this wiſdom of the World found to be fooliſhneſs, and not able to fathom, or comprehend, or give the knowledg of the things of God, which are ſpiritual, which ſeeth over and above all deceit and deceiveableneſs of unrighteouſneſs, ſet up in the Worldly principle, in the carnal mind, which canot pleaſe God, being at enmity againſt the Seed of God, in which he is well pleaſed, out of which all your ſervices and worſhips are but abomination in the ſight of the Lord, which maketh deſolate, being but falſe coverings of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> while he rules in the heart; and ye ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come to know a ſeparation made in the earth, between the ſeed of the Serpent and the <hi>ſeed</hi> of the Woman working in the heart of man; by one of which two powers, all creatures are guided and led forth to act, and until ye come to true judgement, in the light to diſcern, ye know not by which power ye are acted, and ſo bring forth nothing but confuſion, and are ſervants of ſin and <hi>Satan,</hi> under a pretence of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and zeal for God; yet all out of the life and power of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58369:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>truth,</hi> whoſe voice muſt be heard, and is known by the ſheep of Chriſt, from all falſe teachers and deceivers, who have put on ſheeps cloathing, but inwardly are ravening Wolves, that rob God and Chriſt of his right <hi>within,</hi> and raven from the ſpirit of life, which ought to be the onely guide to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the performance of duties towards God and man; all other performances, are but images and likeneſſes of things begotten and brought forth from a falſe power, crying up <hi>ſelf-righteouſneſs without,</hi> and let ſin and iniquity reign <hi>within,</hi> from which corrupt root, all that proceeds is but bitter fruit.</p>
            <p>It is the great deſign of Antichriſt to keep people from the power of God <hi>within (Chriſt in us)</hi> and to perſwade them to high performances in the imaginations and imitation without which pleaſeth the carnal mind, and makes, pahaps, a fair ſhew in the fleſh. But this child, though as goodly as <hi>Iſhmael</hi> that came from <hi>Abrahams</hi> loynes after the fleſh, yet it is not the heir of the promiſe according to the Covenant of life. Aſſuredly <hi>that which is begotten of God, and brought forth of a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, is the heir of Gods Kingdome;</hi> all other are but falſe births from the ſeed of the bond-woman, which with her ſon, though never ſo ſtately, is to be caſt out, and not to be heir with the ſon of the free-woman. <hi>Let</hi> him that hath an Ear hear what the ſpirit ſaith: <hi>Judas</hi> the Traytor hath gotten himſelf into an high form of words; Hail Maſter, and kiſſed him, much for deceitful greetings, as moſt falſe teachers are, and the Phariſees that crucifie the Lord of life, can make clean the out-ſide of the <hi>cup</hi> and <hi>platter. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs your righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs exceed theirs, ye ſhall not enter into Gods Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pilate</hi> being warned of the woman (that was in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) may waſh his hands, and yet give unjuſt judgement to crucifie the innocent <hi>Lamb of God.</hi> The higheſt and greateſt Profeſſors of the letter and words without, can joyn unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly together to cry out againſt <hi>the life (within</hi> the City of Gods habitation) crucifie him, crucifie him, and ſo carrie him without the Gates (where are Dogs, Sorcerers, and Whoremongers, and Murtherers, and Idolaters, and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever loveth and maketh a lye) there the Lord of life is put to death.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:58369:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Wolves</hi> in ſheeps cloathing, counterfeits that deceive the World, having killed Gods <hi>witneſs within,</hi> they hate, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute and devour Gods witneſſes without, whoſe teſtimony is from the life of truth, which diſcovers all their falſe coverings, they having loſt the ſheeps nature <hi>within,</hi> they make it their work to prey upon and deſtroy Gods Lambes without, whoſe blood cryes loud from the earth for vengeance upon thoſe ungodly and wicked men, thoſe idol ſhepheards, that ſell ſouls for morſels of bread and handfulls of Barley; thoſe Miniſters of unrighteouſneſs, who by their lyes and lightneſs have cauſed thouſands to err from the truth of God, running greedily after the errour of <hi>Balaam</hi> for the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of unrighteouſneſs, that are called of men Maſter, who loves the uppermoſt ſeats in the Synagogues, <hi>receive honour one of another as unbelievers do;</hi> and many follow their pernicious ways, whereby the way of truth is evil ſpoken of, blind guides, haters of the light, deceitful, heady, high-minded, proud, covetous, whoſe ſpots of uncleanneſs are ſeen in their fleſh without, proceeding from the power of <hi>darkneſs within,</hi> which rules in the hearts of the children of diſobedience: workers of inqiuity they are, the ſeed of evil doers, that ſay and do not, that under pretence make long prayers to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, faſt and pray to ſmite with the fiſt of wickedneſs, and to murther the juſt, who is more righteous then themſelves; Curſed children they are, ſuch as the Lord hates, and never ſent them in his ſervice, neither do they his work, but the works of their father the Devil they do, who was a lyar from the beginning, and aboad not in the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And will</hi> this people alwayes follow the errour of the wicked, and believe in lyes, and never <hi>come to the Light</hi> to try the ſpirits that are gone forth into the world; Know you not that the Scriptures of truth teſtifie, That that ſpirit is true that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth that Chriſt is come in the fleſh, for <hi>the grace of God</hi> teacheth us to deny ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and to walk righteouſly, ſoberly, and godly in this preſent world. And do not theſe <hi>deceivers</hi> live in the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eye, and the pride of life, and are they not of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt?</hi> Try them by their fruits, they are made manifeſt.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58369:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Do men gather Grapes of Thorns, and Figgs of Thiſtles? Believe them not, for there is a lying ſpirit in the mouth of theſe Prieſts, and falſe Prophets, and be ye ſeparate and come out from amongſt them, and partake not any longer with them in their ſins, leaſt ye alſo partake with them in their Plagues, which aſſuredly ſhall fall upon this wicked Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of men, that will not have the Lord to be the Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of his people.</p>
            <p>How long will ye give your ſelves up to ſottiſhneſs, blinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ignorance, as not to come to <hi>the Light,</hi> that you may ſee where you and they are in the <hi>Dark</hi> under falſe cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: What cry them up for <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt,</hi> which ſhould be cloathed upon with the <hi>robes</hi> of his righteouſneſs, made <hi>white</hi> in the blood of the Lamb? Try them, are they ſuch? Nay, verily they are ſuch as have dyed their garments <hi>red</hi> with the blood of Chriſts Saints and ſervants, read the truth hereof in their barbarous and <hi>bloody</hi> cruelty, acted upon the bodies and goods of the people called <hi>Quakers</hi> throughout <hi>England,</hi> the Saints of the moſt high God they are ſo, and the Lord will own them to be ſo, to the ſhame and confuſion of all their enemies, though now they gnaſh their teeth at them, and grin like Dogs, crying out, help, help, O Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, or elſe we are undone, or the like of that; A confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy, a confederacy, report, and we will report it, and make lyes their refuge, which from the beginning <hi>to the end</hi> hath been the practice of their Father the Devil. <hi>Balak</hi> and <hi>Balaam</hi> together conſult againſt this people, that are come up over againſt them, whoſe God is the Lord great and mighty.</p>
            <p>The Prieſts and People, Jews and Gentiles, combine to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to <hi>betray the Son of man into the hands of ſinners.</hi> The beaſt and falſe Prophet, the <hi>Whore</hi> arrayed in Purple and Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let colour, that ſits upon many waters, peoples, <hi>Tongues</hi> and Languages the <hi>Prieſts original,</hi> Myſtery <hi>Babylon,</hi> the mother of Harlots, falſe Churches and falſe worſhippers have made themſelvs drunk with the blood of the Saints that have ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Teſtimony of <hi>Jeſus;</hi> Yet would have People believe that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is their <hi>Saviour:</hi> So drunk are people with the Whores cup of Fornications, that they are blinde and given
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58369:7"/>up to believe lyes; they can ſit at eaſe in the fleſh, and talk of God and Chriſt afar off, but cannot indure that the truth ſhould come nigh them.</p>
            <p>What, is the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of God <hi>within,</hi> is the <hi>light within, Chriſt</hi> to be known <hi>within,</hi> the <hi>word</hi> nigh thee in thy heart and in thy mouth? Truly this may ſeem ſtrange, that that God whom ye have ignorantly worſhipped ſo long afar off, ſhould be ſo nigh in the heart, and doth God require truth in the inward parts, where <hi>Satans</hi> reign and Kingdom hath ſo long been, and muſt that old houſholder of iniquity be turned out withal his deceitful Merchandize and profitable crafts? This ſets all the world in an uproar that lyeth in wickedneſs, and the witneſs of God begins to make the wicked cry out, let us alone, Why art thou come to torment us before the time? Muſt it be ſo indeed, that Chriſt alone muſt have the Kingdom? and may not Pride, Covetouſneſs, and other luſts of the fleſh and works of darkneſs ſtand with this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God in the heart of man and in the world to be ſet up? Nay, out muſt all ſin and iniquity, all thy old lovers, pleaſures, profit, honour, credit, all muſt be forſaken for Chriſts ſake, or elſe thou ſhalt never be found worthy of him; and as thou haſt in thy unregenerate eſtate been wholly a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of ſin, ſo now in the regeneration thou muſt wholly and faithfully follow Chriſt the Saviour to redeem thee from all ſin, and give thy ſelf up, body, ſoul and ſpirit, a living ſacrifice unto God, that ſo being <hi>in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> thou mayeſt with him in Gods dominion (which man loſt in the fall) <hi>reign</hi> with him in righteouſneſs over all deceit and unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, within and without, and in God thy maker live, move, and have thy being.</p>
            <p>Is it ſo (ſome may ſay) this ſeems to be hard ſayings, and who then ſhall be ſaved? what muſt we leave all in truth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deceit? yea, and deny your ſelves as the Scriptures te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie, and take up the dayly croſs to the carnal mind that hath gone a whoring after falſe worſhips and ſtrange Gods, that the <hi>enmity</hi> may be <hi>deſtroyed</hi> that's <hi>in you,</hi> or elſe ye cannot be Chriſts Diſciples, nor witneſſes of the word of Reconciliation, without which ye cannot be ſaved, whatever other hopes ye have, they are but dead hopes, and ſuch as ye ſhall be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58369:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>It's an eaſie matter to read and talk of the way to life, to be a ſtrait and narrow way, and that few there be that find it, and to talk of Chriſts ſufferings at <hi>Jeruſalem; Death and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> hath heard the fame of wiſdom and can preach thereof, but to witneſs the ſtraightneſs of the way to the Kingdom, and the meaſure of Chriſts ſufferings to be fulfilled in your ſelves, without which ye ſhall not reign with him in glory; This you will finde not to be a work of fleſh and blood, nor accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will of man, but a work wrought by the arm of Gods ſalvation, that can give life to the duſt of the earth; That all <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Magicians ſhall be made to know and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to the truth of God, that this is the Finger of God.</p>
            <p>Know ye not, or hath the God of this World wholly blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded your eyes, that the Devils rage appeareth and the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of iniquity then works ſtrongly, when the life and power comes nigh him that deſtroyes his work and kingdom. <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah</hi> and his mighty Hoſt rageth mightily when <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould be gone out of his bondage to ſerve the living God. The Scribes and Phariſees, Prieſts and Elders, Rulers and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple can delight themſelves to talk of the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets which fore-tell of Chriſts coming, and can make an outward profeſſion accordingly, and can build again the Tombes of the Prophets and adorn the Sepulchers of the Juſt; Yet when the <hi>Juſt and Holy one</hi> comes, they are all of an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roar, and the Devil is ſo high in them, that they charge him that he caſt out Devils by <hi>Belzebub</hi> the Prince of Devils (what ſtrange deceit and wickedneſs is this, think ye, in profeſſors of the letter) that accounted Chriſts life madneſs, and thoſe that followed him fools and mad men, and though the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which they had teſtified of him, yet they would not come to him that they might have life, but deſpiſed, rejected, and ſcorned both him and his Doctrine, and never left lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſnares, and watched by falſe accuſations to intrap him, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til they had moſt ſhamefully crucified him, accounting him not worthy to live. <hi>They crucifie the life and ſet another to bear the croſs,</hi> as all you formal profeſſors in <hi>England</hi> do this day, who reject the croſs of Chriſt, whereby the enmity ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed in you, that the life of righteouſneſs might there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58369:8"/>which ſuffers by your formed weapons; writing at top of the croſs in ſeveral Languages, <hi>This is the King of the Jews:</hi> In your vain imaginations, ſaying, Loe here, loe there, and wote not that the <hi>Kingdom of God is within you,</hi> where Chriſt hath long waited to reign; But ye would not have this man to reign over you, but have ſent him out of your Coaſts, and having <hi>loſt</hi> the ſence of his <hi>life within,</hi> are making likeneſſes to your ſelves from the Letter without, ſeeking for him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Jeruſalem below,</hi> not minding where <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Aegypt</hi> (ſpiritually ſo called) are, where darkneſs, pride, and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of bread, luſts and uncleanneſs are where the Lord is crucified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cain</hi> ſlew <hi>Abel</hi> in the beginning becauſe he was more righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous then himſelf, and his Sacrifice was accepted with God, but <hi>Cains</hi> was not.</p>
            <p>The beaſt and falſe Prophet, <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> and all the Armies of the Aliens, thoſe that are ſtrangers to Gods <hi>Covenant of Light,</hi> they now rage and make war againſt the <hi>witneſs</hi> of God, the <hi>Lamb</hi> ſlain from the foundation of the world, now raiſed from death to life to execute righteous judgements up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the workers of iniquity; ſurely this muſt needs trouble the world, becauſe their deeds are evil. Come down all ye high and lofty ones from the mountains and hills that ye have ſet up in your vain imaginations unto the <hi>pure principle of God in you,</hi> that will ſhew you that God is worſhipped neither in this mountain nor at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but in ſpirit and in truth, no longer in the oldneſs of the letter, but in newneſs of the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>And this as a witneſs for the Lord, I teſtifie and declare to all the world, that all other worſhips and worſhippers, though they make never ſo fair a ſhew in the fleſh, all their faſtings, prayers, preachings, ſabbaths, ſingings, and other perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances are all abominable in the ſight of the Lord, no better then the cutting off a Doggs Neck, or the offering of Swines blood, being a burden to the Lord, the which his ſoul is wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to bear.</p>
            <p>Know O man what ever thou art that pleadeſt againſt perfection in this life for any one ſin, either pride, covet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, drunkenneſs, ſwearing, lying, or what ever it be,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58369:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>(let thy cloak or pretence be never ſo colourable) in thee the Devil hath his Kingdom by conſent, and doeſt thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſalvation from them which thou delighteſt to live in? Knoweſt thou not, there is no fellowſhip between Chriſt and <hi>Belial,</hi> no communion between <hi>light</hi> and <hi>darkneſs;</hi> and he that is joyned to an Harlot, is one with the Harlot, and he that breaketh one of Gods Commandements is guilty of the whole?</p>
            <p>Truly the Lord God of heaven and earth hath waited long to be gracious to this Nation, and hath often called them to repentance by his <hi>witneſs within,</hi> and viſited them by his meſſengers and ſervants early and late for ſeveral years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but they have hardned their hearts and ſtiffned their necks, caſt the councels of the Lord behind their backs, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted and ſcornfully intreated, and deſpitefully uſed his meſſengers, that the Lord God is grieved with this wicked Generation that have choſen their own wayes, and rejected and ſet at nought <hi>Chriſt Jeſus the way to everlaſting life,</hi> whoſe right it is to reign, on whom the Government is laid, and he ought to be the <hi>King and Law giver</hi> in theſe Nations. And all ye wiſe builders and ſetters up of worſhips and governments in your fallen wiſdom which is out of Gods Councel, have but robbed God and Chriſt of their right. Know ye not that your wiſdom is confounded, and ye do but contract ſhame to your ſelves? What think ye, pot-ſhards of the earth, that ye can ſtand againſt the Lord God Almighty? Nay, aſſuredly he will overturn, overturn, and overturn all your forms and frames of Worſhips and Governments ſet up without him; ſee ye not how your enterprizes have been blaſted, and your deſignes againſt the Lord and his Chriſt fruſtrated? yea and ſo ſhall all the Councels of the ungodly periſh, and the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the wiſe be turned into fooliſhneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Know ye not,</hi> ye Sects, Formaliſts, and Notioniſts, that ye have <hi>betrayed the juſt and righteous principle of God in you,</hi> from whence liberty, reformation, righteous Laws and freedom ſhould flow forth, that ſo from the good old cauſe, ye are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated into the bad old principle, and having no better hopes, are gone down again into <hi>Aegypt</hi> for councel and help from the Lords enemies <hi>into the dark, ye are gone backward from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58369:9"/>the light,</hi> ye are waxen fat with <hi>Geſhurun,</hi> and have forgotten the Lord, who brought you up out of the houſe of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and ſet you above all the Nations round about you.</p>
            <p>O ye ſtrong men of the Nations and ſometimes valiants of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who hath bewitched you with <hi>Sampſon</hi> to give your ſtrength into <hi>Dalilahs</hi> lap, that Harlot that will betray you into the hands of the <hi>Philiſtines?</hi> and take heed leaſt the end be the ſame, deſtruction upon <hi>Sampſon</hi> and the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; let them that know themſelves concerned herein by the witneſs of God in them conſider what is ſaid, leaſt ſudden deſtruction come upon them, and repentance be hid from their eyes, for the Lords ſpirit is grieved with this people, and cannot indure that men ſhould deal ſo deceitfull in his work, that after God hath planted them in Vineyards, and given them to eat the fruit of the Vine, they ſhould rebel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him and revolt as back-ſliding <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that they ſhould take the Son of the husbandman and kill him, that they may have his inheritance. This is great unkindneſs indeed, that men ſhould thus requite the Lord. What, think ye that ye can hide your ſelves from the Lord? Nay, verily he will ſurely ſearch and find out thoſe rebels that will not have his Son to reign over them. What are the Princes of this people become the companions of thieves &amp; robbers, that murther up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the way by conſent? How is that City wherein righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs did ſometime lodge, now become an Harlot?</p>
            <p>How are thoſe that have talked of and waited for the coming of Chriſts Kingdom now turned Apoſtates, to ſet up their own greatneſs inſtead of Chriſts righteouſneſs amongſt men? how have theſe people forſaken the Lords Councel given them by his ſervants, and have taken councel with the ungodly, againſt him that will break them to pieces and rule them with an iron rod?</p>
            <p>How long will ye neglect the day of your viſitation? Verily the Lord will not be mocked, and let not the long ſuffering of God be ſo much abuſed, for his Spirit ſhall not alwayes ſtrive with men. Know this of a truth, that if once that day paſs over your heads, ye are undone for ever, and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance ſhall be for ever hid from your eyes, as it is already paſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58369:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>upon many in this Nation that have ſlighted and rejected Gods call. What ever falſe reſts or confidence ye build upon, or what deceitful coverings ſoever ye put on, they will prove too ſhort and too narrow to hide you from the wrath of the Lamb in the day of the Lords reckoning with you, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens; Therefore put not far away the evil day, but repent, and return, and work while ye have <hi>Light,</hi> while it is called to day, for the night cometh when no man can work. Look not back what others have been, or what others have done, but minde your own meaſure and talent given of God to every one to profit withal, for according to the talent recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, every mans account and reward ſhall be.</p>
            <p>The everlaſting light of the Son of God hath ſhined forth and been preached amongſt you of this Nation, unto which ye ſhould have been turned, that ſo ye might be brought from under Satans power into the power of God. Yea ſuch riches of love hath God ſhewed to this Nation, that not any Nation in the World, at this time, hath known the like for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of himſelf in the glorious light of the Goſpel; to the end, that if they knew the day of their viſitation, and the things that belong to their peace, they might be the firſt fruits of faith unto God of the whole earth, witneſſes of the firſt reſurrection of the Juſt and righteous government of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Truly the Lord hath done much for this people, and he expects much from them; but behold, inſtead of bringing forth much fruit unto the Lord, they are turned into a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Wilderneſs full of bryars and thorns; and unleſs they ſpeedily repent and turn from the evil of their wayes, and come down to own Gods witneſs in them, and bring all their glory and crowns to the feet of the Lamb, they may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect no other but certain fearful judgments to be powred out upon them from the righteous hand of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Friends,</hi> this know, that until ye come to own and follow the light, ye remain in darkneſs, and are out of the way to Gods Kingdom, for the light is the way, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus the light of the World, the way to the Father,</hi> that hath inlightned every man that cometh into the World, even that voice in thee what ever thou art, that ſhews thee the evil of thy wayes, and oftentimes reproves and condemns ſin in thee, the ſame <hi>is the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58369:10"/>grace of God</hi> that bringeth ſalvation, which hath appeared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all men, and therefore look not for another; <hi>this is the way</hi> that a way fairing man, though a fool, ſhall not err in, as all in this way muſt become fools, if ever they expect to be wiſe unto ſalvation.</p>
            <p>In this way Reformation, Liberty, and Freedom, ſo long contended for, is to be found, <hi>Chriſt in us the hope of Glory,</hi> the ſum of the whole matter, the beginning and end of all: and what ever ye do without him, ye are but uſurpers, and reign without God in the World, and all your buildings that are not upon this foundation ſhall not ſtand, but prove as a rotten and broken wall that ſhall be overturned and ſhattered to pieces.</p>
            <p>I ſay again, and on the Lords behalf challenge it to be <hi>Chriſts right to reign,</hi> and ye are but uſupers that keep him out of his Kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And according</hi> to the word of the Lord which came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me at <hi>Bridgewater,</hi> in the County of <hi>Sommerſet,</hi> on the fifth day of the ninth moneth, 1659. The burden whereof I have felt and born in much bitterneſs of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the life of Gods witneſs in me being preſſed down as a Cart with ſheaves, by reaſon of the wickedneſs of this people, which is very great; (After the ſpace of 24 dayes) have written and again proclaim as the word of the Lord God to you all, high and low, rich and poor, young and old, Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants and people of <hi>England,</hi> to whom ſoever this paper ſhall come, whoſe day is not paſt. <hi>Repent, Repent, for the Kingdom of Heaven is at hand, and the patience and long ſuffering of God is almoſt at an end.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Bridge water, <hi>writen on</hi> 
                  <date>the 29 of <hi>the</hi> 9th. <hi>Moneth,</hi> 1659.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>John Anderdon.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:58369:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
